<chapter id='after_installation'><title>After Installation</title>

<sect1><title>Checking Your Configuration File</title>

<para>Once you have installed <application>apcupsd</application>, either
from a binary package or by building from source, your next step
should be to inspect your <filename>/etc/apcupsd/apcupsd.conf</filename>
file to make sure it is valid.</para>

<para>You can read the complete <link
linkend='directive_reference'>reference on configuration
directives</link>, but if you are setting up a normal standalone 
configuration you should only need to check (and possibly fix) the
first three items listed below.</para>

<para>Your UPSTYPE should be the UPS's protocol type: dumb, apcsmart,
usb, net, or snmp.  Your UPSCABLE should be the type of cable you are
using.  You should have gotten both from the <link
linkend='type_table'>table of types</link>; usually they will both
be the string "usb".</para>

<para>If you have a USB device, it is better not to specify a
DEVICE directive by commenting it out. <application>Apcupsd</application> will automatically 
search for your device in the standard places.
If you specify a DEVICE, it should be the name of the device (or device range)
that <application>apcupsd</application> is to use to communicate with
the UPS.  If you're using a USB UPS under Linux, you may leave
the device name field blank and <application>apcupsd</application>
will search all the standard locations for the UPS. You
may also explicitly specify the device location as
either <filename>/dev/usb/hid/hiddev[0-15]</filename> (on non-Red-Hat
systems) or <filename>/dev/usb/hiddev[0-15]</filename> (on Red Hat
systems). Note, please enter the device names <emphasis>exactly</emphasis>
as written above brackets, numbers, dash and all.</para>
<para>
If the first time you execute <application>apcupsd</application>, you get
a message to the effect that the Apcupsd USB driver is missing, it means
that you most likely forgot to put <emphasis>--enable-usb</emphasis> on
your <filename>./configure</filename> command line. If you loaded        
<application>apcupsd</application> from an rpm file, you may have
selected the wrong one -- please ensure that the word <emphasis>usb</emphasis>
appears in the rpm package name.
</para>


<para>The <link linkend="config-examples">next chapter</link> of this
manual provides you with the essential characteristics of each main type
of configuration file.  After those elements are correct, apcupsd should
run, and then it is only a matter of customization of your setup.</para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id='autoboot'><title>Arranging for Reboot on Power-Up</title>

<para>The final consideration for a automatic reboot after a full
power down is to ensure that your computer will automatically reboot
when the power is restored.</para>

<para>This is not the normal behavior of most computers as shipped
from the factory. Normally after the power is cut and restored, you
must explicitly press a button for the power to actually be turned
on. You can test your computer by powering it down; shutting off the
power (pull the plug); then plugging the cord back in. If your
computer immediately starts up, good. There is nothing more to
do.</para>

<para>If your computer does not start up, manually turn on the
power (by pressing the power on button) and enter your computer's
SETUP program (often by pressing DEL during the power up sequence;
sometimes by pressing F10). You must then find and change the
appropriate configuration parameter to permit instant power
on.</para>

<para>Normally, this is located under the <emphasis
role="bold">BOOT</emphasis> menu item, and will be called something
such as <emphasis role="bold">Restore on AC/Power Loss</emphasis> or
<emphasis role="bold">Full-On</emphasis>. The exact words will vary
according to the ROM BIOS provider. Generally you will have three
options: <emphasis role="bold">Last State</emphasis>, <emphasis
role="bold">Power On</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">Power
Off</emphasis>. Although <emphasis role="bold">Last State</emphasis>
should normally work, we recommend setting your computers to <emphasis
role="bold">Power On</emphasis>. This means that whenever the power is
applied they are on. The only way to shut them off is to pull the plug
or to have a special program that powers them off
(<filename>/sbin/poweroff</filename> on Linux systems).</para>

<para>If after making all the changes suggested above, you cannot get
your computer to automatically reboot, you might examine your halt
script (<filename>/etc/rc.d/init.d/halt</filename> in the case of
Red Hat Linux) and see if the final line that performs the halt or
reboot contains the <option>-p</option> option for powering down the
computer. It should not with the logic used by
<application>apcupsd</application>, but if it does, the
<option>-p</option> option could cause your computer to power off
while the UPS is still suppling power (i.e. before the UPS kills the
power).  Depending on the setting of your BIOS, it may prevent your
computer from restarting when the power returns. As already mentioned,
this should not apply, but in case of problems it is worth a
try.</para>

</sect1>
<sect1><title>Making sure <application>apcupsd</application> Is Running</title>

<para>The simplest way to invoke <application> apcupsd</application>
is from the command line by entering:</para>

<programlisting>
/sbin/apcupsd
</programlisting>

<para>To do so, you must be root. However, normally, you will want
<application>apcupsd</application> started automatically when your
system boots. On some systems with installation support (e.g. SuSE
and Red Hat), the installation procedure will create a script file that
you will be automatically invoked when your system reboots. On other
systems, you will have to invoke <application>apcupsd</application>
from your <filename>rc.local</filename> script.</para>

<para>On Red Hat systems, this script file that automatically invokes
<application>apcupsd</application> on system start and stops is:
<filename>/etc/rc.d/init.d/apcupsd</filename></para>

<para>To start <application>apcupsd</application> manually (as you
will probably do immediately following the installation), enter the
following:</para>

<programlisting>
/etc/rc.d/init.d/apcupsd start
</programlisting>

<para>To understand how this file is automatically invoked at system
startup and shutdown, see the man pages for <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>chkconfig</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>.</para>

<para>On SuSE systems, the script file that automatically invokes
<application>apcupsd</application> on system start and stops is
<filename>/etc/rc.d/apcupsd</filename></para>

<para>To start <application>apcupsd</application> manually (as you
will probably do immediately following the installation), enter the
following:</para>

<programlisting>
/etc/rc.d/apcupsd start
</programlisting>

<para>Normally, when properly installed,
<application>apcupsd</application> will be started and stopped
automatically by your system. Unfortunately, the details are different
for each system. Below, we give the commands for selected
systems. Alternatively, there are simple
<application>stopapcupsd</application> and
<application>startapcupsd</application> scripts in the examples
directory, or you can modify one of the scripts in the distributions
directory to meet your needs.</para>

<para>To stop <application>apcupsd</application> you can do the
following:</para> 

<para>On Red Hat systems:</para>

<programlisting>
/etc/rc.d/init.d/apcupsd stop
</programlisting>

<para>On SuSE systems:</para>

<programlisting>
/etc/rc.d/apcupsd stop
</programlisting>

<para>
Please see the <link linkend="testing">Testing Apcupsd</link> chapter for more   
details on insuring that <application>apcupsd</application> is running
properly.</para>

</sect1>
</chapter>
